Preliminary Inventory to the Roger A. Freeman Papers, 1950-1990
Hoover Institution Archives
Roger A. Freeman Papers,
1950-1990
75053
Freeman, Roger A., 1904-
489 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize boxes, 1 card file box (21 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, speeches and writings, printed matter, and slides, relating to governmental problems in the state of Washington, 1950-1955, fiscal problems of Bolivia, 1957, international economic development, taxation (federal, state, and local), intergovernmental relations in the United States, public and private education from lower schools to university in the United States and the Soviet Union, and the growth of American government.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is stored off-site. It may be possible to have a limited number of boxes brought to the archives reading room for examination. A minimum of two days notice is required. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Biographical/Historical Note
American economist; senior fellow, Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace, 1962-1975; special assistant to President Richard M. Nixon, 1969-1970.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, speeches and writings, printed matter, and slides, relating to governmental problems in the state of Washington, 1950-1955, fiscal problems of Bolivia, 1957, international economic development, taxation (federal, state, and local), intergovernmental relations in the United States, public and private education from lower schools to university in the United States and the Soviet Union, and the growth of American government.
Access Points
Economic development.; Education.; Education--Soviet Union.; Education--United States.; Finance, Public--Bolivia.; International economic relations.; Public welfare--United States.; Bolivia.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); United States--Politics and government.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; Washington (State)--Politics and government.; Conservatism.; Economists.; Slides (Photography)
Container List
- Speeches and Articles (Box 1)
  - Philadelphia Society, Los Angeles, 1972
  - Journal of Public Law, Emory University, March 1972
  - AEI, School Finance Conference, March 1972
  - New York Times, "Will Money Improve Our Schools," March 1972
  - Wall Street Journal, "Should the States Take Over School Finance," March 1972
  - National School Boards Association Convention, San Francisco, April 1972
  - School Finance Presentation, Governor's Office, Sacramento, April 1972
  - Proxmire letter (4/19/72), reply (4/26/72)
  - California Social Welfare Department, Economic Research, April 1972
  - Testimony of Tax Credit Bill, California Assembly Rev. and Tax Comm., May 1972
  - High School Debate Manual, School Finance, AEI, Drafts, 1972-73
  - High School Debate Manual, School Finance, AEI, Drafts, 1972-73 (Box 2)
  - High School Debate Guide, 1972-73
  - Non-coersive Education, National Review - Drafts
  - ISI - Stanford, August 1972 (Box 3)
  - Reading Form Foundation, Annual Conference, San Francisco, July-August 1972
  - A.C.I.R. - Property Tax Relief and School Aid, August-December 1972
  - Republican Platform Committee, Miami, August 1972
  - Pennsylvania School Boards Ass. Convention, Philadelphia, September 1972
  - National Economy and Implications for Public Managers, Executive Seminar Center, September 1972
  - Fellowship Form, November 1973
  - Foundation for Researching and Economics and Education, Los Angeles, December 1972
  - Latter Day Alchemists in Education, Modern Age, Summer 1972
  - Property Taxation and the Finance of Education
  - Governor's Task Force on Expenditure Reduction, 1972-73
  - Governor's Task Force Lawsuit, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Freedoms Foundation Award, 1973, Wayward Welfare State
  - Philadelphia Society, Chicago, April 1973
  - The Impact of Theory on Policy, Executive Seminar Center, Berkeley, April 1973
  - Conference on Poverty, Ohio, 1973
  - Review - "The Rape of the Taxpayer," Human Events, April 1973
  - Tax Loopholes - AEI, 1972-73
  - Tax Loopholes - AEI, Sons in Retirement, Rickey's Palo Alto, June 1973 (Box 5)
  - Fact and Fiction about Tax Loopholes, Applied Christianity
  - Income Tax Reforms Seminar - NTA - TIA, July 1973, Washington
  - ISI Summer School, Mon-Mouth, Annual Conference, NTA-TIA, Toronto-Ontario, September 1973
  - Sons in Retirement, October 1973
  - Assembly, California Legislature - Assembly Com. on Education, October 1973, S.F., Calif., Prop. 1
  - U.S. Economy Status and Prospects, NAEBM, Newport Beach, October 1973
  - Proposition 1, The Tax Reduction Initiative, Portola Valley Town Meeting, October 1973
- Africa
  - General, travel arrangements, October 1973
  - Brazil, October 29 - November 1973
  - South Africa, Rhodesia, November--December
  - Zambia-Taiwan, December-January
  - Hawaii
- Advisory Council on Financial Aid to Students (Box 6)
  - March 1974
  - June 1974
  - January 1974
- Advisory Commission on Inter-Governmental Relations
- American Enterprise Institute (Box 7)
- American Security Council
- Anderson, Dr. Martin A.
- B
- Baroody, William J., Junior
- British Airways
- Buchanan, Patrick J.
- RR
- Center for Independent Education
- College/University Corporation
- Burkhart, John B.
- Citizens for Educational Freedom
- The Conservative Caucus
- Council for American Private Education
- D
- Donner Foundation
- E
- Evans, William S.
- F
- Freedom Foundation at Valley Forge
- Freeman, Roger A., biographical sketch, 1975
- Freeman, Roger A., 1968-1974 (Box 8)
- G
- Governmental Research Association
- H
- Heritage Foundation
- Hoeber, Francis P.
- Hoover Institution
  - General
  - Campbell, W. Glenn (Box 9)
  - Campbell, Rita R.
- Human Events
- Howard, Dr. John, President, Rockford College
- I
- Inter-collegiate Review
- J
- K
- Kemp, Jack
- L
- Loeffler, Mr. Theodore B., World Research Inc.
- M
- Mackay, A. Calder, Esquire
- Mc
- McMullen, Penny
- The Milwaukee Society
  - General
  - Speech, Wisconsin, William H. Brady Jr., October 17, 1974
- Miscellaneous
- Mont Pelerin Society
- N
- National Conference on American Federalism in Action
- National Education Association, Washington, D.C.
- National Review
- National Task Force on Student Aide Problem
- National Tax Association - Tax Institute on America
- National Tax Association - Committee on Inter-governmental Fiscal Relations
- O
- P
- Pacific Legal Foundation, Sacramento, California
- Pepperdine University
- Philadelphia University
- The Philadelphia Society
- Public Choice in Education
- Q
- R
- Republican Study Committee
- Richardson-Merrell, Inc.
- S
- Shockley, William D. (Box 10)
- Smith, Dan Throop
- Stanford University
- T
- Taylor, Clifford W.
- U
- V
- W
- Wall Street Journal
- Ware, Richard A.
- Wilkinson, Richard A.
- William Volker Fund
- Williams, Professor Duncan
- World Affairs Council of Northern California
- XYZ
- Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations: National Conference on American Federalism, 1/22/75 - 1/24/75
- Commonwealth Club of California, April 17, 1974 - "Evolution or Revolution in Southern Africa"
- Lou Henry Hoover Building, Polich Room, April 16, 1974 - "Evolution or Revolution in Southern Africa"
- Professor William Peterson
- Graduate School of International Management, Glendale, Arizona, April 17-18, 1974
- World Affairs Council, April 23, 1974 - "Evolution or Revolution in Southern Africa"
- Public Affairs Fellowship Program, April 29, 1974 - "The Moyhihan Report and the Politics of Controversy"
- Mont Pelerin Society Meeting, Census Advisory Meeting, 8/20 - 9/20, 1974
- Stanford University - Hoover Centennial, Los Angeles, October 23, 1974 - U.S. Government "Most Ebullient Growth History"
- California Department of Benefits Payments Project, Delphi, March 1975
- "Role of Government in Private vs. Public Education," February 2-7, 1975, Hillsdale College, Michigan
- Review of West article "Aid to Private Schools," March 1975 (Box 11)
- Letter to Wall Street Journal, "Quota Question," March 31, 1975
- International I
  - General Statistics and Sources
  - Economic Development, 1967-1972
  - International Assistance
    - 1968-1970
    - to 1967 (Box 12)
  - Foreign Investment Policies
  - Food
  - Education
  - International Organizations
  - Other
  - Africa
    - General
      - 1972-
      - 1967-1971 (Box 13)
      - 1964-66
      - pre-1964
- International II
  - B-1 - Projection of population and economy (So. Africa)
  - B-2 - a) Economic background (So. Africa)
  - B-2 - b) Employment - Trade Unions and Wages
  - B-3 - Foreign investment in So. Africa
  - B-4 - Apartheid, extent of oppression and international comparisons (Box 14)
  - B-5 - Apartheid - the Politics of Reform
  - B-6 - Governmental Programs: Benevolance or Benefits
  - B-7 - Homeland Solidarity and Demands
  - B-8 - Prospects of Federalism
  - B-9 - International Diplomacy and So. Africa
  - B-10 - Education
  - C - Kenya
  - D - Ethiopia
  - E - Zambia
  - F - Rhodesia (Box 15)
  - G - Nigeria
  - H - Uganda
  - I - Mozambique and Angola
  - J - Zaire
  - K - Tanzania
- International III (Asia, Europe and Latin America)
  - A - Asia General
  - B - Middle East
    - -1917
    - to 1970 (Box 16)
    - Iran and Afghanistan
    - India
    - Pakistan
    - India, Ceylon, Nepal, 1964-
    - India, Ceylon, Nepal, -thru 1963
  - C - Southeast Asia, General (Box 17)
    - Indonesia
      - - to 1970
      - - 1971-
    - Malaysia and Singapore
    - Vietnam
    - Other
  - D - Far East, General
    - China (Box 18)
    - Hong Kong
    - Japan
    - Mongolia
- International IV (Europe, General)
  - Europe, 1963
  - Europe
- International V (Latin America)
  - A - General
    - - 1964
    - - 1965
    - - Panama 1965
    - - Panama 1965 (Box 19)
  - B - Latin America, General, 1963
  - C - Bolivia
    - 1961-65
    - 1958-1960 (Box 20)
  - D - Brazil
- International VI (U.S.S.R.)
  - General
  - 1964-65
- Speeches and articles, 1963-65
  - Tax Bill Testimony, Senate Finance Committee, November 1963 (Box 21)
  - Rotary Club, Milwaukee, November 1963
  - National Conference on Government, Detroit, November 17-20, 1963 (National Municipal League)
  - Comments on HEW Release on classroom shortage in the public schools, 2/17/64
  - Foreword to the American edition of Welfare, Freedom and Inflation, by William Roepke, July 1964 (Box 22)
  - Seminar, University of Wisconsin, June 11-20, 1964
  - Intercollegiate Society of Individualists, Inc., 8/25-8/26/1964
  - Fiscal Grants to States, Memo for Tom Curtis, August 1964
  - Senior Colloquim, 1964
  - Stanford Alumni, Los Angeles
  - Sc #13, 1964 term papers
  - "What Makes Ivan Run?" speeches on U.S.S.R. trip, 1965
  - School Aid Testimony, House-Senate, February 1965 (Box 23)
  - National Review, "How to Railroad a School Aid Bill," May 18, 1965
  - Speeches on aid to education, 1965
  - Income Tax Credits (for H.E.), 5/20/65
  - Service State at Mid-Century, APSA, 4/14/65
  - Soviet Education, Benton article, National Review
  - The Armed Services and the Charmed Services, National Review, 9/11/65 AS & CS, misc. (Box 24)
  - Senior Colloquium, Autumn, 1965
  - Tables for SC Tax Reform, Fall 1965
  - Blair, Jack
  - Pidduck, Kurt
  - Merchants and Manufacturers Association (Annual Management Conference, Palm Springs, October 24, 1965)
  - Balance of Payments, Senator Dirksen, November 1965
  - Federal Grants-in-Aid, National Tax Conference, November 1965
  - Campus Debate "Role of Federal Government Increased?" November 17, 1965 (Box 25)
  - Crisis in College Finance
    - Page proofs
    - Correspondence, 1965-
    - Correspondence, 1963-64
    - Reviews
    - Complimentary copies
    - Promotion
    - Review copies
    - Announcements
  - Big Government, Friend or Foe, San Diego, January 9, 1966 (Box 26)
  - Misc. speeches, 1966
  - Big Government, Friend or Foe, Long Beach, February 19, 1966
  - Crisis in College Finance, Milwaukee Society, March 1966
  - Philadelphia Society, National Meeting, Civil Right and Individual Responsibilities, Chicago, March 4-5, 1966
  - Consumer Credit Controls, House Banking Committee, April 1966
  - Public Employment Potential, Nation, 5/66
  - Big Government, Friend or Foe, Long Beach, 5/5/66, Santa Monica, 5/6/66
  - Independent Action - Education Employment, Dependency, R-Cornvello-Walton, May 1966
  - Brigham Young University, DR.h.c. 5-66 (Box 27)
  - Education Tax Credits, College Entrance Exam Board, May 22-25
  - Forbes, June 1, 1966, The Affluent Professors
  - Freedoms Foundation - Government and the Economy, July 13, 1966
  - Inter-collegiate Society of Individualists Seminar - Economics, August 22-26, 1966
  - Mont Pelerin Society, Tokyo
  - Federal Aid Cities League of California Cities, annual meeting, Chicago, 10-17-66
  - National Assistance League, 10-26-66 (Box 28)
  - Matean Mosaic TV Panel Discussion, 11-8-66
  - Philadelphia Society meeting, November 18-19, 1966, San Francisco
  - Meetings, New York - Dearborn, Ill.
  - Tax Sharing, memo for Rep. Laird Barwood, Jr., December 29, 1966
  - Letter to the editor, New Republic, "Who Gets in the Army," January 1967
  - George Washington Medal Freedom Foundation, February 22, 1967
  - What Makes Ivan Run, National Review, March 7, 1967
  - What Makes Ivan Run, 1967
  - ASPA Panel, March 28, 1967, Federal Funds and Local Budgets
  - Letter on James article, Stanford Today, Summer 1967
  - Study group on tax sharing, Republican Coordination Committee
    - February-March 1967
    - April-May 1967 (Box 29)
    - June-July 1967
    - August-December 1967
    - -1968
  - Inter-governmental Council on Urban Growth
  - Senior Colloquium, 1967-68
  - Forum International, Berkeley, August 22, 1967 (Box 30)
  - Time, July 7, 1967
  - Menlo Park - Live Oak Lions Club, September 18, 1967
  - National Civic Review, September 1967
  - 50 Year USSR-Communism Conference, Hoover Institution, October 9-13, 1967
  - Soviet economy
  - The Freedom Budget, St. Raymonds Catholic Church, Menlo Park, 10/18/67
  - National Tax Association Conference, Atlanta GA, October 22-26, 1967
  - Rational Debate Seminars, AEI, Washington, October 26, 1967
  - The Fellowship Forum, Palo Alto, November 7, 1967
  - Tax Institute Symposium, Federal-State-Local Relationships, Washington, D.C., 11/29/67 - 30/11/67
- Speeches and articles, 1968 - July 1969
  - UROC - January 25, 1968 (Box 31)
  - Bolivia, Christian Freedom Foundation, 2/20/68
  - Republic Alliance, March 5, 1968
  - California Tax Reform, March 1968
  - Socialism and Private Enterprise in Equatorial Asia
    - Announcements
    - Distribution
    - Promotion
    - Reviews
    - Correspondence
  - Republican Platform, May 1968
    - for Senator Dirksen and other material
    - Governor's Task Force Hearing, SF, CA
  - World Affairs Are Your Affairs, Radio KNBR, July 7, 1968
  - Socialism and Private Enterprise in Equatorial Asia, Radio KNBR, 6/30/68
  - Big Government and Republican Party
  - The Frustrating Task of Trying To Teach the Disadvantages (Box 32)
    - Wall Street Journal, July 1968
    - Correspondence
  - Kaiser Broadcasting, Joe Dolan, August 14, 1968
  - Tax Sharing, Federal Executives Seminar, Berkeley, September 18, 1968
  - International Economic Seminar, SF, October 15, 1968 (World Affairs Council)
  - Executive Seminar Center, Berkeley, 10/21-11/1/68 (Box 33)
  - Palo Alto Kiwanis Club, November 14, 1968
  - Review of Brodin manuscript, November 1968
  - Hoover Institution Advisory Board Meeting, New York, December 4, 1968
  - Income Maintenance Programs, New York, December 5, 1968
    - Correspondence
    - Copies of speech
    - Material
  - Philadelphia Society, SF, December 6-7, 1968
  - Still Chasing the End of a Rainbow, Southern Education Report, January 1969
  - Baker Revenue Sharing Proposal, 1/9/69
  - Dead End in American Education, National Review, January 14, 1969
  - Goals and Limits of Governmental Action in a Free Society, 1/31/69, Executive Seminar Center, Berkeley (Box 34)
  - Stanford Conference in Southern California, February 16, 1969
  - Public Affairs Fellowship Program, February 25, 1969
  - Financing Private Higher Education Alchemists in the Public Schools, Distribution Harper's Magazine, "Our Latter Day Alchemists"
  - Tax Reform, LA Times, March 1969 (Box 35)
  - George Washington Masonic Club, May 26, 1969
  - Federal Assistance to Higher Education Through Income Tax Credits, JEC, 6/69
  - VSA Funds, "LOANS," 1969
  - Student Loan Programs (USAF and ABA), May-July 1969
- Speeches and articles, August 1969 - January 1972
  - Hoover Institution, "Big Government," August 17-23, 1969 (Box 36)
  - Current Programs to Meet US Social Problems, National War College, 9/16/69
  - National Tax Association Conference, Boston, MA, September 29 - October 3, 1969
  - American Association of Independent College and University Presidents' Annual Meeting, October 7, 1969
  - U.S. News Interview, January 26, 1970, Education Planes
  - 34th Annual Pennsylvania Local Government Finance Conference, Harrisburg, PA, January 29-30, 1970
  - "Why Don't They Stop Inflation?" Eastern Regional Conference of Assoc. Credit Bureaus, NYC, February 1970
  - "Crisis in Education," June 19, 1970, Washington State Research Council, Seattle, correspondence
  - "Crisis in Education," June 19, 1970, Washington State Research Council, Seattle, correspondence (Box 37)
  - Banking, Journal of the American Bankers Association, July 1970
  - Polich Room, Lou Henry Hoover Building, July 8, 1970
  - Executive Seminar "Administration of Public Policy: Interactions Between the Economy and Public Policy," U.S. Cir. Service Commission, August 4, 1970, Berkeley, CA
  - Federal Aid to Higher Education in the 91st Congress, State Higher Education Commissions Organizations, August 6, 1970, Burlington, Vermont
  - "The Wayward Welfare State," Governmental Research Association. September 1, 1970, magazines, newspapers, etc.
  - San Marino City Club (Stanford Alumni Office), San Marino, CA, 9/15/70 (Box 38)
  - Contemporary Tax Problems, National Tax Association, Honolulu, 9/20-9/25
  - National Industrial Conference Board, Cleaveland, Ohio, 9/29/70
  - Stanford Debate Square, October 1970
  - Interaction of the Economy and Public Policy, Berkeley Executive Seminar Center, October 13, 1970
  - Math and Aftermath, 10/22/70, California Elementary School Administrators Association
  - National Priorities in the Decade Ahead, Stanford Conference, Los Angeles, 11/8/70
  - Beta Alpha Psi, "Political Involvement of the University," 11/19/70
  - Philadelphia Society Regional Meeting
  - The Advocates, Station KCET, December 1, 1970
  - Elmhurst College, P. Gamma Mu, December 3, 1970
  - Indonesia, 1970
    - Southeast Asian region
    - Commercial environment
    - Foreign investment
    - Labor
    - Expatriate management
    - Logistics
    - Finance and taxation
  - Ness International, December 1, 3, 7, NY, Chicago, SF
  - Revenue Sharing Report, 12/70, A.E.I.
  - San Jose State Home Economics Class, "Inflation," 1/13/71 (Box 39)
  - The American Political Tradition, Philadelphia Society, Chicago, 4/2-3/71
  - Palo Alto Kiwanis Club, 4/15/71
  - The Arabs and the Israelis - An Overview of the Middle East, World Affairs Council, 5/20/71
  - Letter of Wage, Price and Profits Freeze, New York Times, 9/8/71
  - Modern Age, Fall 1971
  - Income Tax Credits for Tuitions and Gifts in Nonpublic School Education, 12/71, prepared by President's Commission on School Finance
  - Income Tax Credits for Tuitions and Gifts in Nonpublic School Education, 12/71, prepared by President's Commission on School Finance (Box 40)
  - League of Women Voters, 12/8/71
  - School Aid Property Tax Relief, AEI, White House, 12/71-72
  - Comment of R.A.F. on H.R.l Committee of Finance, U.S. Senate
    - January 27, materials pertaining to Senate development
    - January 27, correspondence
    - January 27, letters re: testimony
    - January 27, Final Statement
    - January 27, Newspaper articles, etc.
    - January 27, drafts (Box 41)
- PROBLEMS IN PUBLIC WELFARE
  - General
    - Criticism of Welfare Programs (Box 42)
    - Answer to Criticism
    - General statistics
  - Poverty (Box 43)
    - Income statistics
    - Unemployed
      - General statistics, labor force (Box 44-45)
      - Automation, productivity
      - Inadaquate demand and purchasing power (Box 45-47)
      - Wage levels
      - Profits
      - Steel and other industries (Box 48)
      - International competition
      - Retraining (Box 49)
      - New entries and dropouts (Box 49-50)
    - Depressed areas
    - Low wage persons; minimum wage (Box 51)
    - Farm labor
    - Problem families (Box 52)
  - The Aged (including private pensions)
  - The Young (Box 53)
    - Juvenile delinquency (Box 53-54)
  - The Ill and Handicapped
  - War On Poverty
  - Voluntary welfare
  - White House Conference on Children and Youth (Box 55)
  - White House Conference on the Aging
  - Ethnic minorities
    - Negroes
      - Political behavior
        - Legislation and court decisions
        - Voting
        - Attitudes
        - Civil rights movement
          - Separatism vs. integration (Box 56)
          - Black militance
          - Riots (Box 56-57)
          - Other
      - Social, cultural and economic status
        - Black history and culture
          - Black studies
        - International comparisons
        - Progress (Box 58)
          - Affirmative Action Programs & discrimination
        - Education
          - School decentralization (community control)
          - Elementary and secondary schools (Box 58-60)
          - Higher education
        - Family and social problems (Box 60)
        - Genetic and environmental factors
        - Crime and delinquency (Box 61)
        - Occupational distribution
          - Black capitalism
        - Union membership (Box 62)
        - Unemployment
        - Income
        - Housing
    - Other minorities
      - Chinese and Japanese (Box 63)
      - American Indians
      - Spanish Americans
      - Other immigrants
    - White House Conference on Civil Rights
    - Other
  - Social Security Act, changes to 1959 (Box 63-64)
  - Social Security Act, 1960
  - Social Security Act, 1961-62
  - Social Security Act, 1963, and appropriations 1964
  - Social Security Act, 1964, and appropriations 1965
  - Social Security Act, 1965, and appropriations 1966
  - Social Security Act, 1966
  - Social Security Act, 1967-1973 (Box 65)
- PUBLIC ASSISTANCE, GENERAL
  - Public Assistance history (Box 65-66)
  - Public Assistance, level of government
    - Welfare load and capacity
    - Grants-in-Aid
    - Source of funds and control
  - Public Assistance, administration
    - Manpower and salaries (Box 67)
    - Workload size and recipient rates
    - Professional vs. lay control
  - Issues in Public Assistance
    - Confidentiality (Box 68)
    - Residence
    - Money payment
    - Eligibility and recipient rates
    - Level of benefits (Box 68-69)
    - Personal responsibility and "deserving"
    - Fraud and chiseling
  - Projections
  - Non-monetary aid (Box 69-70)
  - Rehabilitation, retraining
- OLD AGE ASSISTANCE (OAA)
  - Recipients (Box 71)
  - Benefits
  - Issues
  - Lien and recovery
  - Relative responsibility
- AID TO CHILDREN AND FAMILIES (Box 71-73)
  - AFDC Program
    - Recipients